There is something about physics
هناك شيئا ما يتعلق بالفيزياء،
that has been really bothering me since I was a little kid.
يضايقني منذ كنت طفلاً صغيرًا ،
And it's related to a question
وهو يتعلق بالسؤال
that scientists have been asking for almost 100 years,
الذي ظل العلماء يسألونه لحوالي 100 عام،
with no answer.
دون إجابة.
How do the smallest things in nature,
كيف تتلائم أصغر الأشياء في الطبيعة،
the particles of the quantum world,
أصغر الجسيمات في عالم الكم،
match up with the largest things in nature --
مع أكبر الأشياء في الطبيعة --
planets and stars and galaxies held together by gravity?
الكواكب والنجوم والمجرات تتماسك معاً عن طريق الجاذبية؟
As a kid, I would puzzle over questions just like this.
كطفل صغير، كانت تحيرني مثل هذه الأسئلة.
I would fiddle around with microscopes and electromagnets,
كنت العب بالميكروسكوبات و المغناطيس ،
and I would read about the forces of the small
و اقرأ عن القوى الموجودة بين الجزيئات
and about quantum mechanics
وحول ميكانيكا الكم
and I would marvel at how well that description matched up
متسائلاً عن مدى دقة ذلك الوصف
to our observation.
مع ما نشاهده.
Then I would look at the stars,
وبعدها انظر الى النجوم ،
and I would read about how well we understand gravity,
وأقرأ عن مدى فهمنا للجاذبية،
and I would think surely, there must be some elegant way
وأفكر أنه بالتأكيد لابد من وجود طريقة أنيقة
that these two systems match up.
لتداخل هذين النظامين بهذا التناغم.
But there's not.
لكن لا يوجد .
And the books would say,
تشير الكتب،
yeah, we understand a lot about these two realms separately,
إننا نعلم الكثيرعن هذين العالمين كل على حدى،
but when we try to link them mathematically,
ولكن عندما نحاول ربطهما ببعض رياضياً،
everything breaks.
كل شئ ينهار.
And for 100 years,
لمئة عام،
none of our ideas as to how to solve this basically physics disaster,
جميع أفكارنا لحل هذه المعضلة الفيزيائية،
has ever been supported by evidence.
لم يتم دعمها بالحقائق و الأدلة .
And to little old me --
بالنسبة لجيمس الطفل--
little, curious, skeptical James --
الصغير ، الفضولي، كثير الأسئلة--
this was a supremely unsatisfying answer.
هذه الاجابة لم تكن كافية على الإطلاق.
So, I'm still a skeptical little kid.
مازلت ذلك الطفل المتسائل.
Flash-forward now to December of 2015,
فلنعد الآن الى ديسمبر من عام 2015،
when I found myself smack in the middle
عندما وجدت نفسي في منتصف
of the physics world being flipped on its head.
عالم الفيزياء المنقلب رأساً على عقب .
It all started when we at CERN saw something intriguing in our data:
بدأ ذلك عندما وجدنا شيء مثير للإهتمام في سيرن (المنظمة الاوروبية للابحاث النووية):
a hint of a new particle,
تلميح لوجود جسيم جديد ،
an inkling of a possibly extraordinary answer to this question.
معلومة صغيرة قد تجيب بشكل استثنائي عن ذلك السؤال.
So I'm still a skeptical little kid, I think,
اعتقد أنني مازلت ذلك الطفل كثير الأسئلة ،
but I'm also now a particle hunter.
ولكنني ايضا الأن باحث عن الجزيئات.
I am a physicist at CERN's Large Hadron Collider,
أنا فيزيائي في مشروع سيرن "مصادم الهدرونات الكبير"،
the largest science experiment ever mounted.
أكبر تجربة علمية انشأت على الإطلاق.
It's a 27-kilometer tunnel on the border of France and Switzerland
وهيا عبارة عن انبوب تحت الحدود الفرنسية السويسرية طوله 27 كم
buried 100 meters underground.
بعمق 200 متر تحت الأرض.
And in this tunnel,
في هذا النفق،
we use superconducting magnets colder than outer space
نستخدم مغانط عالية التوصيل أكثر برودة من الفضاء الخارجي
to accelerate protons to almost the speed of light
لتسريع حركة البروتونات لما يقارب سرعة الضوء
and slam them into each other millions of times per second,
و جعل الجزيئات تتصادم ببعضها البعض ملايين المرات في الثانية الواحدة،
collecting the debris of these collisions
نقوم بتجميع نواتج ذلك التصادم
to search for new, undiscovered fundamental particles.
بحثاً عن جزيئات أولية جديدة لم يتم اكتشافها.
Its design and construction took decades of work
استغرق تصميمه وبنائه عقود من العمل
by thousands of physicists from around the globe,
وعمل عليه آلاف الفيزيائين من جميع أنحاء العالم ،
and in the summer of 2015,
و في صيف 2015،
we had been working tirelessly to switch on the LHC
كنا نعمل بكامل جهدنا لتشغيل المصادم "مصادم الهدرونات الكبير"
at the highest energy that humans have ever used in a collider experiment.
بأعلى طاقة استخدمها البشرعلى الإطلاق في تجارب التصادم.
Now, higher energy is important
الآن ، الطاقة الأعلى مهمة
because for particles, there is an equivalence
لأن بالنسبة للجزيئات هناك تعادل
between energy and particle mass,
بين الطاقه و كتلة الجسيم .
and mass is just a number put there by nature.
و الكتلة هي مجرد رقم وجد من الطبيعة.
To discover new particles,
لإكتشاف جسيمات جديدة ،
we need to reach these bigger numbers.
نحنا بحاجه للوصول لتلك الأرقام الكبيرة .
And to do that, we have to build a bigger, higher energy collider,
لعمل ذلك ، يتحتم علينا بناء مصادم أكبر بطاقة اكبر ،
and the biggest, highest energy collider in the world
المصادم الأكبر والأعلى طاقة في العالم
is the Large Hadron Collider.
هو مصادم الهدرونات الكبير(LHC)
And then, we collide protons quadrillions of times,
ثم نقوم بمصادمة البروتونات كدريليون مرة "كدريليون =ألف تريليون"
and we collect this data very slowly, over months and months.
ثم نقوم بتجميع هذه البيانات بتأني على مدار شهور وشهور.
And then new particles might show up in our data as bumps --
وبالتالي قد تظهر فجأة جسيمات جديدة من هذه البيانات----
slight deviations from what you expect,
انحراف بسيط عن ما توقعنا،
little clusters of data points that make a smooth line not so smooth.
مجموعة صغيرة من نقاط البيانات ، والتي لا تجعل الخط الأملس أملساً جداً .
For example, this bump,
على سبيل المثال، هذه المفاجأة،
after months of data-taking in 2012,
بعد شهور من تجميع البيانات في 2012
led to the discovery of the Higgs particle --
أدت الى اكتشاف جسيمات هيغز
the Higgs boson --
هيغز بوزون
and to a Nobel Prize for the confirmation of its existence.
ولجائزة نوبل لإثبات وجودها .
This jump up in energy in 2015
زيادة الطاقة هذه في 2015
represented the best chance that we as a species had ever had
تمثل أفضل فرصة أننا كنوع قمنا
of discovering new particles --
باكتشاف جسيمة جديدة
new answers to these long-standing questions,
تجاوب عن تلك الأسئلة طويلة الأمد ،
because it was almost twice as much energy as we used
لأنها تحتوي على طاقة مضاعفة عن ما اعتدنا عليه
when we discovered the Higgs boson.
عندما اكتشفنا هيغز بوزون
Many of my colleagues had been working their entire careers for this moment,
العديد من زملائي عملوا حياتهم كلها للوصول الى هذه اللحظة ،
and frankly, to little curious me,
وبصراحة ، لقد أثارت اهتمامي قليلاً ،
this was the moment I'd been waiting for my entire life.
تلك كانت اللحظة التي كنت انتظرها طوال حياتي.
So 2015 was go time.
اذاً سنة 2015 كانت سنة منطلقة
So June 2015,
و في يونيو 2015 ،
the LHC is switched back on.
قمنا بإعادة تشغيل LHC
My colleagues and I held our breath and bit our fingernails,
قمت أنا وزملائي في العمل بحبس أنفاسنا وقرض أظافرنا ،
and then finally we saw the first proton collisions
وعندها وأخيراً رأينا أول تصادم البروتون
at this highest energy ever.
في أعلى مستوى طاقة .
Applause, champagne, celebration.
تصفيق ، شامبانيا ، واحتفالات .
This was a milestone for science,
كانت هذه قفزة للعلم ،
and we had no idea what we would find in this brand-new data.
لم يكن لدينا أي فكرة عن ما سنراه في هذا التاريخ الجديد
And then a few weeks later, we found a bump.
وبعدها بعدة أسابيع وجدنا عثرة .
It wasn't a very big bump,
ليست بعثرة كبيرة ،
but it was big enough to make you raise your eyebrow.
لكنها كانت كبيرة بما فيه الكفاية لتجعلك ترفع حاجبك .
But on a scale of one to 10 for eyebrow raises,
لكن في مقياس من 1 الى 10 لرفع الحاجب ،
if 10 indicates that you've discovered a new particle,
اذا كانت 10 تشير الى اكتشاف جسيم جديد ،
this eyebrow raise is about a four.
فإن رفع هذا الحاجب يشير الى أربعة .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
I spent hours, days, weeks in secret meetings,
لقد أمضيت ساعات ، أيام وأسابيع في اجتماعات سرية ،
arguing with my colleagues over this little bump,
وأجادل زملائي في العمل ، حول تلك العثرة ،
poking and prodding it with our most ruthless experimental sticks
نبحث ونتجادل حول عصا التجارب التي لاترحم .
to see if it would withstand scrutiny.
لمعرفة اذا كانت ستصمد ضد التدقيق
But even after months of working feverishly --
لكن حتى بعد شهور من العمل الكثيف
sleeping in our offices and not going home,
والنوم في مكاتبنا وعدم الذهاب للمنزل ،
candy bars for dinner,
وأكل قطع الحلوى كعشاء ،
coffee by the bucketful --
وشرب القهوة بكاسات كبيرة
physicists are machines for turning coffee into diagrams --
الفيزيائيين هم آلات لتحويل القهوة الى مخططات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This little bump would not go away.
هذه العثرة الصغيرة لم تتحرك .
So after a few months,
اذاً بعد عدة شهور ،
we presented our little bump to the world with a very clear message:
قدمنا عثرتنا الصغيرة للعالم مع رسالة واضحة :
this little bump is interesting but it's not definitive,
هذه العثرة الصغيرة مثيرة للإهتمام لكنها ليست حاسمة ،
so let's keep an eye on it as we take more data.
اذاً دعونا نبقي أعيننا عليها بينما نجمع المزيد من البيانات .
So we were trying to be extremely cool about it.
اذاً حاولنا أن نبقى هادئين قدر المستطاع حولها .
And the world ran with it anyway.
والعالم تأقلم معها على كل حال .
The news loved it.
الأخبار أحبوا هذا .
People said it reminded them of the little bump
قال الناس أنها تذكرهم بالعثرة الصغيرة
that was shown on the way toward the Higgs boson discovery.
والتي ظهرت في طريق اكتشاف هيغز بوزون
Better than that, my theorist colleagues --
والأفضل من ذلك ، زملائي النظريين
I love my theorist colleagues --
أحب زملائي النظريين
my theorist colleagues wrote 500 papers about this little bump.
كتب أصدقائي الفيزيائيين 500 ورقة حول هذه العثرة الصغيرة .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The world of particle physics had been flipped on its head.
انقلب عالم الفيزياء التطبيقية رأساً على عقب .
But what was it about this particular bump
لكن ما السبب الذي يجعل تلك العثرة
that caused thousands of physicists to collectively lose their cool?
تفقد آلاف الفيزيائيين هدوئهم ؟
This little bump was unique.
هذه العثرة الصغيرة مميزة .
This little bump indicated
تعبر هذه الجزيئة الصغيرة
that we were seeing an unexpectedly large number of collisions
أننا نرى عدد كبير غير متوقع من التصادمات
whose debris consisted of only two photons,
والتي تتكون من حطام فوتونين اثنين
two particles of light.
جزيئتين من الضوء .
And that's rare.
وهذا شيء نادر.
Particle collisions are not like automobile collisions.
تصادم الجزيئات ليس كتصادم السيارات
They have different rules.
لديهم قوانين مختلفة.
When two particles collide at almost the speed of light,
عندما يتصادم جزيئين فهما بسرعة الضوء تقريباً،
the quantum world takes over.
حينها تبدأ قوانين عالم ميكانيكا الكم
And in the quantum world,
وفي العالم الكمي ،
these two particles can briefly create a new particle
هذان الجزيئان الصغيران يستطيعان خلق جسيم صغير لفترة وجيزة
that lives for a tiny fraction of a second
والذي يعيش لجزء صغير من الثانية
before splitting into other particles that hit our detector.
قبل أن يتجزأ لجسيمات صغيرة تصطدم بكاشفنا .
Imagine a car collision where the two cars vanish upon impact,
تخيل تصادم سيارات حيث تختفي كلا السيارتين بسبب التصادم
a bicycle appears in their place --
وتظهردراجة هوائية في مكانهما--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then that bicycle explodes into two skateboards,
وعندها تتفجر تلك الدراجة الهوائية الى لوحي تزلج ،
which hit our detector.
والتي تصطدم بكاشفنا .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Hopefully, not literally.
نأمل ذلك ، وليس حرفياً .
They're very expensive.
أنهم مكلفين جداً .
Events where only two photons hit out detector are very rare.
حتى عندما يصطدم فوتونان على كاشفنا فهذا شيء نادر الحدوث جداً .
And because of the special quantum properties of photons,
وبسبب خصائص الكم للفوتونات ،
there's a very small number of possible new particles --
هذه اعداد صغيرة جداً من الجسيمات الممكنة
these mythical bicycles --
هذه الدراجات الإسطورية --
that can give birth to only two photons.
والتي تولد فوتونين اثنين فقط .
But one of these options is huge,
لكن احد هذين الخيارين ضخم ،
and it has to do with that long-standing question
ويتعلق بذلك السؤال القديم
that bothered me as a tiny little kid,
والذي أزعجني عندما كنت طفلاً صغيراً،
about gravity.
حول الجاذبية .
Gravity may seem super strong to you,
قد تبدو الجاذبية قوية جداً بالنسبة لك ،
but it's actually crazily weak compared to the other forces of nature.
لكنها في الحقيقة ضعيفة مقارنة ببقية القوى في الطبيعة .
I can briefly beat gravity when I jump,
أستطيع بسهولة هزم الجاذبية عندما أقفز .
but I can't pick a proton out of my hand.
لكن لا أستطيع أن أخذ بروتون من يدي.
The strength of gravity compared to the other forces of nature?
قوة الجاذبية مقارنة ببقية قوى الطبيعة ؟
It's 10 to the minus 39.
انها من 10 أس ناقص 36 .
That's a decimal with 39 zeros after it.
هذا رقم عشري ب 36 صفر بعده .
Worse than that,
والأسوء من ذلك ،
all of the other known forces of nature are perfectly described
جميع قوى الطبيعة المتبقاة مشروحة بشكل واضح
by this thing we call the Standard Model,
عبر هذا الشيء الذي نسميه النموذج الأساسي ،
which is our current best description of nature at its smallest scales,
وهو وصفنا الحالي الأكثر دقة لأصغر المقاييس في الطبيعة .
and quite frankly,
وفي الحقيقة .
one of the most successful achievements of humankind --
أحد أعظم الإنتصارات للبشرية --
except for gravity, which is absent from the Standard Model.
باستثناء الجاذبية ، والتي تكون غائبة في النموذج الأساسي
It's crazy.
هذا جنون .
It's almost as though most of gravity has gone missing.
الأمر تقريباً وكأن الجاذبية فُقدت تماماً .
We feel a little bit of it,
نحن نشعر بالقليل بها .
but where's the rest of it?
لكن أين بقيتها ؟
No one knows.
لا أحد يعرف .
But one theoretical explanation proposes a wild solution.
لكن تقترح أحد التفسيرات النظرية حل جامح .
You and I --
أنا وأنت --
even you in the back --
وحتى أنت في الخلف --
we live in three dimensions of space.
نحن نعيش في فضاء ثلاثي الأبعاد .
I hope that's a non-controversial statement.
أتمنى أن يكون هذا بيان غير قابل لإثارة الجدل .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All of the known particles also live in three dimensions of space.
جميع الجسيمات المعروفة تعيش في فضاء ثلاثي الأبعاد .
In fact, a particle is just another name
في الحقيقية ، الجسيم هو أسم آخر
for an excitation in a three-dimensional field;
للوجود في مجال ثلاثي الأبعاد .
a localized wobbling in space.
فضاء متذبذب
More importantly, all the math that we use to describe all this stuff
والأهم من ذلك ، جميع الرياضيات التي استخدمناها لوصف كل تلك الأشياء
assumes that there are only three dimensions of space.
تفترض وجود ثلاث أبعاد للفضاء .
But math is math, and we can play around with our math however we want.
لكن الرياضيات هي الرياضيات ، ونستطيع اللعب مع الرياضيات كيفما شئنا.
And people have been playing around with extra dimensions of space
وكان الناس يلعبون بأبعاد جديدة للفضاء
for a very long time,
لوقت طويل جداً ،
but it's always been an abstract mathematical concept.
لكنه كان مفهوم رياضي مجرد طوال الوقت .
I mean, just look around you -- you at the back, look around --
اعني ، انظرو حولكم، وأنتم في الخلف، انظروا حولكم
there's clearly only three dimensions of space.
هذا واضح أنه فضاء ثلاثي الأبعاد .
But what if that's not true?
لكن ، ماذا لو كان هذا غير صحيح ؟
What if the missing gravity is leaking into an extra-spatial dimension
مااذا لو كانت الجاذبية المفقودة تتسرب لتصبح أبعاد آخرى إضافية
that's invisible to you and I?
هل هذا مرئي لك ولي ؟
What if gravity is just as strong as the other forces
ماذا لو كانت الجاذبية قوية كبقية القوى
if you were to view it in this extra-spatial dimension,
واذا استطعت النظر اليه من البعد الخارج المكاني
and what you and I experience is a tiny slice of gravity
وما نختبره أنت وأنا هو شريحة صغيرة من الجاذبية
make it seem very weak?
ويجعلها تبدو ضعيفة جداً ؟
If this were true,
اذا كان ذلك صحيحاً .
we would have to expand our Standard Model of particles
سيكون علينا أن نوسع النموذج القياسي للجسيمات
to include an extra particle, a hyperdimensional particle of gravity,
ولنضيف جسيمة إضافية ، جسيمة فائقة الأبعاد من الجاذبية
a special graviton that lives in extra-spatial dimensions.
غرافتيون خاص يعيش في بعد خارج مكاني .
I see the looks on your faces.
أنني أرى النظرة في وجوهكم.
You should be asking me the question,
عليكم أن تسألوني سؤال
"How in the world are we going to test this crazy, science fiction idea,
كيف علينا بحق الرب أن نختبر فكرة الخيال العلمي هذه ،
stuck as we are in three dimensions?"
ونحن عالقون في ثلاثة أبعاد ؟
The way we always do,
كما كنا دائماً .
by slamming together two protons --
عن طريق تصادم بروتونين معاً --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Hard enough that the collision reverberates
من الصعب بما فيه الكفاية حدوث الاصطدام
into any extra-spatial dimensions that might be there,
في أي بعد خارج مكاني والذي يمكن أن يكون ثلاثة .
momentarily creating this hyperdimensional graviton
خلق لحظة من كرافتيون متعدد الابعاد
that then snaps back into the three dimensions of the LHC
ثم يستقر مرة آخرى في أبعاد ثلاثية من LHC
and spits off two photons,
ويبصق فوتونين اثنين
two particles of light.
جسيمين من الضوء
And this hypothetical, extra-dimensional graviton
وهذا الكرافتيون في الفضاء المتعدد الابعاد
is one of the only possible, hypothetical new particles
هو الجسيم الافتراضي الجديد الممكن
that has the special quantum properties
والذي يحوي على خصائص الكم الخاصة
that could give birth to our little, two-photon bump.
والتي من الممكن أن تكون عثرتنا الصغيرة من الفوتونيين
So, the possibility of explaining the mysteries of gravity
اذاً إمكانية شرح الغموض الذي يلم بالجاذبية
and of discovering extra dimensions of space --
واكتشاف أبعاد آخرى في الفضاء
perhaps now you get a sense
ربما بدأت تفهم الأن
as to why thousands of physics geeks collectively lost their cool
ولماذا آلاف من مهووسي الفيزياء فقدوا هدوئهم بشكل جماعي
over our little, two-photon bump.
حول عثراتنا الصغيرة
A discovery of this type would rewrite the textbooks.
اكتشاف من هذا النوع سيعيد كتابة كتب الفيزياء
But remember,
لكن تذكروا ،
the message from us experimentalists
والرسالة من الفيزيائيين التجريبيين
that actually were doing this work at the time,
الذين كانوا يقومون بالعمل في هذا الوقت ،
was very clear:
كانت واضحة جداً:
we need more data.
نحتاج لبيانات أكثر.
With more data,
بالمزيد من البيانات ،
the little bump will either turn into a nice, crisp Nobel Prize --
فإن هذه العثرة قد تتحول الى جاائزة نوبل جميلة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or the extra data will fill in the space around the bump
أو الييانات الإضافية ستحل محلها في الفضاء حول العثرة
and turn it into a nice, smooth line.
وتحولها الى خط أملس لطيف .
So we took more data,
ثم جمعنا بيانات أكثر ،
and with five times the data, several months later,
وبخمسة أضعاف البيانات التي جمعناها لاحقاً بعد شهور ،
our little bump
عثرتنا الصغيرة
turned into a smooth line.
تحولت الى خط أملس .
The news reported on a "huge disappointment," on "faded hopes,"
واحتوت نشرات الأخبار على عبارات مثل " إخفاق كبير " ، " خيبة امل كبيرة "
and on particle physicists "being sad."
وغلب الحزن على الفزيائيين العمليين
Given the tone of the coverage,
ونظراً للهجة التغطية الإعلامية
you'd think that we had decided to shut down the LHC and go home.
كنت لتعتقد بأننا سنغلق الLHC ونعود لمنازلنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
But that's not what we did.
لكن لم يكن هذا ماقمنا به .
But why not?
لكن لم لا ؟
I mean, if I didn't discover a particle -- and I didn't --
أعتقد ، اذا لم اكتشف ذلك الجسيم ، ولم أفعل
if I didn't discover a particle, why am I here talking to you?
اذا لم اكتشف الجسيم ، لما أنا أحدثكم هنا؟
Why didn't I just hang my head in shame
لم لم أعلق رأسي بخجل
and go home?
وأذهب للمنزل ؟
Particle physicists are explorers.
الفزيئيين التطبيقيين هم كالمستكشفين .
And very much of what we do is cartography.
وأغلب ما نقوم به هو رسم الخرائط .
Let me put it this way: forget about the LHC for a second.
دعني أشرح لكم بهذه الطريقة : انسوا أمر LHC لثانية
Imagine you are a space explorer arriving at a distant planet,
تخيل بأنك مستكشف فضاء وصل لتوه الى كوكب بعيد ،
searching for aliens.
يبحث عن المخلوقات الفضائية.
What is your first task?
ماالذي سيكون مهمتك الأولى ؟
To immediately orbit the planet, land, take a quick look around
ستلقي فوراً نظرة خاطفة وسريعة على مدار هذا الكوكب
for any big, obvious signs of life,
عن أي علامات كبيرة وواضحة للحياة ،
and report back to home base.
وتقدم تقرير للقاعدة
That's the stage we're at now.
هذه هي المرحلة التي نحن فيها الأن
We took a first look at the LHC
ألقينا نظرة أولية على LHC
for any new, big, obvious-to-spot particles,
لأي جسيمات جديدة واضحة عليه
and we can report that there are none.
ونستطيع أن نبرهن عدم وجود شيء
We saw a weird-looking alien bump on a distant mountain,
وراينا عثرة صغيرة على جبل بعيد ،
but once we got closer, we saw it was a rock.
لكن عندما اقتربنا لاحظنا بأنها حجرة .
But then what do we do? Do we just give up and fly away?
لكن الآن ماذا علينا ان نفعل ؟ هل نستسلم ونطير بعيداً ؟
Absolutely not;
بالتأكيد لا .
we would be terrible scientists if we did.
سنكون علماء فاشلين جداً اذا ما قمنا بذلك .
No, we spend the next couple of decades exploring,
لا ، لقد أمضينا العقدين التاليين نستكشف ،
mapping out the territory,
ونرسم الخرائط
sifting through the sand with a fine instrument,
ونبحث بالرمل بأداة ما
peeking under every stone,
وننظر تحت كل حجر،
drilling under the surface.
ونحفر تحت السطح .
New particles can either show up immediately
الجسيمات الجديدة قد تظهر فوراً
as big, obvious-to-spot bumps,
تبدو كبيرة ، ومن السهل عندها ملاحظة المطبات ،
or they can only reveal themselves after years of data taking.
أو يمكن أن تظهر نفسها بعد سنوات من تحليل البيانات .
Humanity has just begun its exploration at the LHC at this big high energy,
بدأت الإنسانية لتوها استكشافها في LHC على هذا المستوى المرتفع من الطاقة ،
and we have much searching to do.
ولدينا المزيد من البحث لنقوم به .
But what if, even after 10 or 20 years, we still find no new particles?
لكن ماذا لو ، حتى بعد 10 أو 20 سنة ، لا نجد جسيمات جديدة ؟
We build a bigger machine.
نبني آلة اكبر .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We search at higher energies.
نبحث بسمتوى الطاقات الأعلى
Planning is already underway for a 100-kilometer tunnel
ويجري العمل حالياً على نفق بطول 10 كيلومتر
that will collide particles at 10 times the energy of the LHC.
والذي ستصطدم به الجزيئات بعشرة مرت أعلى طاقة من LHC
We don't decide where nature places new particles.
لا نقرر أين ستضع الطبيعة تلك الجزئيات الجديدة .
We only decide to keep exploring.
نقرر فقط أن نستمر بالبحث
But what if, even after a 100-kilometer tunnel
لكن ماذا لو ، حتى بعد نفق بطول 100 كلومتر
or a 500-kilometer tunnel
أو 500 كيلو متر
or a 10,000-kilometer collider floating in space
أو حتى 10.000 كيلو متر لمصادم يطير في الفضاء
between the Earth and the Moon,
بين الأرض والقمر ،
we still find no new particles?
ولا نجد بعد المزيد من الجزيئات ؟
Then perhaps we're doing particle physics wrong.
اذاً ربما نحن نقوم بالفيزياء التطبيقية بشكل خاطئ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Perhaps we need to rethink things.
ربما علينا إعادة التفكير بالأشياء .
Maybe we need more resources, technology, expertise
ربما نحتاج للمزيد من المصادر ، والتقنيات ، والخبراء .
than what we currently have.
عن ما نملكه حالياً .
We already use artificial intelligence and machine learning techniques
نحن نستخدم حالياً تقنيات الذكاء الصنعي وتعليم الآلة
in parts of the LHC,
في بعض أجزاء ال LHC
but imagine designing a particle physics experiment
لكن تخيل تصميم تجربة فيزياء تطبيقية
using such sophisticated algorithms
باستخدام خوارزميات متطورة جداً
that it could teach itself to discover a hyperdimensional graviton.
والتي يمكن أن تعلم نفسها أن تكتشف غرافتيون عديد الأبعاد .
But what if?
لكن ماذا لو ؟
What if the ultimate question:
ماذا لو كان السؤال النهائي :
What if even artificial intelligence can't help us answer our questions?
ماذا لو لم يكن بقدرة الذكاء الاصطناعي اجابتنا عن سؤالنا ؟
What if these open questions, for centuries,
ماذا لو بقيت تلك الأسئلة مفتوحة لسنين ،
are destined to be unanswered for the foreseeable future?
مقدر لها ان تبقى بدون إجابات للمستقبل المنظور؟
What if the stuff that's bothered me since I was a little kid
ماذا لو أن الأشياء التي تزعجني منذ كنت طفلاً صغيراً
is destined to be unanswered in my lifetime?
من المقدر لها أن تبقى بلا أجوبة طوال حياتي ؟
Then that ...
عندها
will be even more fascinating.
سيكون الأمر أكثر روعة
We will be forced to think in completely new ways.
سيكون علينا أن نبدأ التفكير بطريقة مختلفة كلياً
We'll have to go back to our assumptions,
سيكون علينا الرجوع الى افتراضنا ،
and determine if there was a flaw somewhere.
ونقرر اذا ماكان هناك عيب في مكان ما .
And we'll need to encourage more people to join us in studying science
وسيكون علينا ان نشجع المزيد من الناس لينضموا لنا ويدرسوا العلوم
since we need fresh eyes on these century-old problems.
لأننا سنحتاج الى عيون جديدة لهذه المشاكل القديمة منذ عدة قرون .
I don't have the answers, and I'm still searching for them.
ليس لدي اجابات ، ومازالت ابحث عنهم
But someone -- maybe she's in school right now,
لكن شخص ما ، ربما لا تزال في المدرسة الأن ،
maybe she's not even born yet --
ربما لم تولد بعد
could eventually guide us to see physics in a completely new way,
قد تقودنا لنرى الفيزياء بطريقة مختلفة كلياً ،
and to point out that perhaps we're just asking the wrong questions.
ولتشير انه ربما نحن نسأل أنفسنا الأسئلة الغلط .
Which would not be the end of physics,
والتي ربما لا تكون نهاية الفيزياء ،
but a novel beginning.
لكن بداية نبيلة .
Thank you.
شكراً لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )